A Guide to the Papers of Dr. Sandra F. McDonald-American Rhododendron Society
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10553-ag
Papers of Dr. Sandra F. McDonald-American Rhododendron Society 1977-1997
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10553-ag
ca. 700 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
This collection bears no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by Sandra F. McDonald of Hampton, Virginia, on January 12, 1998.
Scope and Content
The papers of Dr. Sandra F. McDonald, ca. 700 items (2 Hollinger boxes, .5 linear shelf feet), 1977-1997, consisting of personal and professional correspondence files pertaining to her interest in rhododendrons and the American Rhododendron Society. Dr. McDonald was a member of the American Rhododendron Society Bylaws Implementation Committee created to formulate a districting plan and to initiate a new election procedure. This is reflected in the folder called American Rhododendron Society-Districting. McDonald has also served as President and Secretary-Treasurer of the Middle Atlantic Chapter of the American Rhododendron Society. She has an advanced degree in horticulture (M.S.) and a doctorate in plant genetics. More frequent correspondents are described below; the rest are summarized in the folder listing.
Her correspondence with William Bedwell, President of the Middle Atlantic Chapter of the American Rhododendron Society, includes several suggested articles and fillers for the MAC Newsletter (Dr. McDonald had been receiving such material as editor of the publication since the inception of the newsletter in 1975). They also discuss other Chapter affairs, including controversy over the need to increase dues (1984; 1985 Mar 7 & 18, Apr 25); the bronze medal given to Ken McDonald and Sandra McDonald from MAC (1984 Jun 13); the MAC ratings committee (1984 Nov 7, 12, 14, 19, & 20); Sandra McDonald declines the editorship of the American Rhododendron Society
Journal
(1984 Nov 12); rhododendron ratings (1985 Jan 2, Jun 3,7, & 10, Nov 15, 1990 Jun 6, Nov 6); heat study (1985 Jan 14, Feb 2); establishing a test garden in Richmond, Virginia (1985 Jan 29, Feb 15); MAC flower show (1986 Feb 4 through Mar 21); and the "Anne Glass" rhododendron (1995 Apr 5, 10, and Jul 19).
Most of her correspondence with John B. Buschmann consists of discussions about propagation of rhododendrons and material for the MAC newsletter. Other topics include daylilies (1985 Jul 15 & Sep 21; and 1986 Jan, Mar 3); the serviceberry (1986 Apr 5, Jun 9); the extremely bad weather (1986 Aug 12); and the restoration of the Trinity Presbyterian Church, New Canton, Virginia(1987 Sep 11).
Sandra McDonald's correspondence with Austin Kennell discusses the rhododendron research fund (1983 Feb 3; 1986 Apr 16); the duties of district directors (1984 Feb 17); dues increases (1984 Feb 17, 27, and Mar 7, 19); Dick Chaiken's report (1986 Mar 28); making the older MAC newsletters available (1986 Oct 30-Nov 25); and the convention in Williamsburg(1988).
Correspondence with Harry Wise include the following subjects: the MAC Newsletter (1983 Nov 11); rhododendron disease compendium (1986 Dec 18); the Blacksburg American Rhododendron Society meeting at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia(1987 Jan 16, 30; Oct 27); nominating committee status reports (1988 Jan 27; 1989 Apr 4); MAC meeting ideas (1988 Feb 22, Mar 8); MAC seed exchange (ca. 1988); issues discussed at the American Rhododendron Society Board meetings (1989 Jan 9, 13 & 27; Aug 24); director's report (1989 Apr 4); the printing of the Breeders Roundtable (1989 Apr 9); native azalea auction (1989 May 10); Canaan Valley meeting (1989 Jun 13 & 17); "Growing Rhododendrons and Azaleas in the Middle Atlantic States" by Dr. Sandra McDonald(1990 Mar 5; Apr 5); ideas for celebration of Earth Day at Coonskin Park and related (1990 Mar 5; Oct 4; 1991 Feb 8); references to the Gulf War (1990 Aug 28); ARS finances (1991 Apr 5); the visit of Tricia Cox and Peter Cox(1991 Jun 17); and slides of native azaleas (1991 Dec 23-1992 Feb 14).
Item Listing
- American Rhododendron Society - Districting, 1980-1983 (Box Box 1)
- Reid Bahnson re rhododendron cuttings, 1988-1992 (Box Box 1)
- William F. Bedwell, 1982-1995; (3 folders) (Box Box 1)
- Breeders' Roundtable, re the sale of the proceedings of the May 15, 1988 Breeders Roundtable held at Williamsburg, Virginia, and moderated by Sandra McDonald, 1989-1994 (Box Box 1)
- John B. Buschman, 1981-1993; (2 folders) (Box Box 1)
- Peter Cox re rhododendron ratings, 1984-1987 (Box Box 1)
- Ian E.M. Donovan re plant breeding, 1977-1986 (Box Box 1)
- William Fetterhoff re rhododendron propagation, 1981-1990 (Box Box 2)
- Joseph Gable Hybrid Plants, 1977-1982 (Box Box 2)
- Fred Galle, Curator of Calloway Gardens re azaleas, 1981-1992 (Box Box 2)
- George Harding re rhododendron breeding, 1977-1978 (Box Box 2)
- Paul James, President of MAC, re MAC business and newsletter, 1989-1993 (Box Box 2)
- Don Kellam, 1987-1988 (Box Box 2)
- Austin Kennell, 1982-1993 (Box Box 2)
- David G. Leach re contract with the McDonald's to introduce the Leach rhododendron hybrids, photographs with 1983 Feb 14, 1978-1986 (Box Box 2)
- Mike McCullough re cuttings of Mary Mayor, 1987-1991 (Box Box 2)
- George K. McLellan re native azaleas on Gregory Bald Mountain in the Great Smokey Mountains National Park, 1994 (Box Box 2)
- Roy Milne re the proposed trip of the ARS to Great Britain, 1990-1991 (Box Box 2)
- Erik Nilsen, VPI botany professor, re his papers about winter leaf movements of rhododendron species and plant hardiness, 1987-1993 (Box Box 2)
- Personal Notes & Post Cards, 1987-1991 (Box Box 2)
- Lonnie M. Player re plant breeding, 1983 (Box Box 2)
- Robert Porter, 1992 (Box Box 2)
- Tony & Marie Shammarello re royalties for his rhododendron hybrids and death in 1982, 1978-1986 (Box Box 2)
- Terry Sheuchenko re Pete Sheuchenko's forms re rhododendron heat tolerance (1989 Aug 16); and MAC newsletter (1991 Aug 6; 1993 Jun 11), 1988-1994 (Box Box 2)
- June Sinclair re a gold medal for the contributions of Peter Cox to rhododendrons, 1991 (Box Box 2)
- Cecil & Molly Smith Garden, 1992 (Box Box 2)
- Dr. Dorothy G. Swift re recruitment for the ARS Speaker's Bureau, 1991 (Box Box 2)
- William Tietjen re seed exchange (1984 Oct 6; 1985 Nov 22); dues increase (1985 Mar 7; Aug 30; Dec 2), 1984-1986 (Box Box 2)
- Harry Wise, 1983-1997; (2 folders) (Box Box 2)
- Linda Wylie, Seed Exchange Chairman, 1992 (Box Box 2)
- Bob Zimmerman re pollen and cuttings of rhododendron, 1984 (Box Box 2)